<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[]]></title>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-19T12:11:13-07:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Processes, Processes, Processes]]></title>
    <link href="/2014/03/03/Processes.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-03T15:58:27-08:00</updated>
    <id>/2014/03/03/Processes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Structured processes are incredibly useful, and often necessary,
beasts.  They are, however, almost never the <em>most</em> important things for a
project.  We shouldn&#39;t hold on to and adhere to processes just because.
Processes are in place to ensure the quality and timeliness of our work.
When they cease to work towards this end, its <em>ok</em> to break the mold.
Live a little sometimes: let go, buck the man, don&#39;t mark that jira ticket
<code>closed</code> even though it&#39;s been deployed, it&#39;ll be ok, I promise.  Say &#39;no&#39; to a
meeting when you&#39;re in the zone getting-shit-done™, tackle a ticket that isn&#39;t
assigned to you, or even <em>gasp</em> fix a bug that hasn&#39;t even been filed yet.</p>

<p>What process have you ignored recently?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated Site Layout]]></title>
    <link href="/2014/03/02/Updated-Layout.html"/>
    <updated>2014-03-02T09:13:57-08:00</updated>
    <id>/2014/03/02/Updated-Layout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Updating my layout for 2014, and switching back to plain
<a href="http://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a>, away from
<a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>.  Octopress was a little too complicated,
did a little too much magic, was confusing/difficult to re-style,
and was much too difficult to maintain/keep up-to-date.</p>

<p>I&#39;m liking plain old <a href="http://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a> +
<a href="htpp://getbootstrap.com">Bootstrap</a> much better, and it actually reduces the
friction to making new posts. So, with that, hopefully I&#39;ll be able to push some
of my thoughts here more frequently this year.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jekyll-Mapping and Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="/2012/07/26/jekyll-mapping-and-octopress.html"/>
    <updated>2012-07-26T11:11:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2012/07/26/jekyll-mapping-and-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a while now, I&#39;ve been wanting to add some sort of maps support to
<a href="http://octopress.org/">octopress</a>/<a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">jekyll</a>,
and I finally recently had some time to look into it a little bit more.
It seems some others out there have had the same idea, because I stumbled
across two plugins that did something close (but not exactly) to what I wanted:
<a href="https://github.com/mguentner/octolayer">octolayer</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/matthewowen/jekyll-mapping">jekyll-mapping</a>.</p>

<p>The reason I&#39;m interested in this is that when I travel, I like to log <code>gpx</code>
tracks of the places we go, and geotag my photos, etc.  It&#39;s nice to be able to
display a map of where I went each day, and I can always go back and find
exactly where that awesome restaurant was (in case I go back, or to tell
friends).</p>

<p>I wasn&#39;t really sure how/if jekyll plugins would map to octopress (since
octopress does use jekyll, but its plugin structure still seems to be slightly
different), so I started off looking into octolayer.</p>

<h2>Octolayer</h2>

<p>Octolayer was only setup to use <a href="http://openlayers.org/">openlayers</a>, and it
could only do specific long/lat co-ordinates.  I really wanted to be able to use
google maps, but I figured i&#39;d give this a try and see how things went.</p>

<p>I liked the way that octolayer was set up, and the ease of installing it, but
the openlayers API looked really messy to me, and I didn&#39;t feel like spending a
bunch of time learning it when I really wanted google maps anyway, so I opened
up an <a href="https://github.com/matthewowen/jekyll-mapping/issues/1">issue</a> with
<a href="https://github.com/matthewowen/">matthewowen</a> to see what his
thoughts were about adding the functionality I wanted to <code>jekyll-mapping</code>.</p>

<h2>Jekyll-Mapping</h2>

<p>Matthew responded pretty quickly, and showed me that he really already had basic
support for what I wanted.  Fantastic.  All you had to do was put this in your
config section of your posts:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">mapping:
    layers:
        - http://path/to/kml_file.kml
        - http://path/to/gpx_file.gpx
</code></pre></div>
<p>Then put this in your post body wherever you want the map to render:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">{% render_map %}
</code></pre></div>
<p>That&#39;s it!  It seemed to work pretty well at first, but then I quickly realized
that the way the code was set up, it would only work on the post page, and would
not be able to display multiple maps on a page that lists several posts (or even
one post with multiple maps).  The javascript used an id to find the
<code>jekyll-mapping</code> element, and it was tightly bound to a single-post page.</p>

<p>I decided to head into <code>#octopress</code> and ask around (I&#39;ve never mucked with
octopress source or plugins before), and got some really useful tips and help
from <a href="https://github.com/imathis">Brandon Mathis</a>, Octopress&#39; creator.</p>

<p>After a bit of tinkering, I ended up with
<a href="https://github.com/throughnothing/jekyll-mapping/compare/refactor">this changeset</a>
that gave me pretty much everything I wanted (for now):</p>

<script src="https://gist.github.com/3183238.js"> </script>

<p>With this, I can put multiple layers on a map (I usually put a <code>.gpx</code> layer for
the day, as well as a layer from flickr with my geotagged photoset for that day
in each relevant post), and display multiple posts, each with a map, per page.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is the number of poor people &quot;declining everywhere&quot;?]]></title>
    <link href="/2012/03/27/is-the-number-of-poor-people-declining-everywhere.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-27T22:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2012/03/27/is-the-number-of-poor-people-declining-everywhere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The economist recently ran an article titled <a href="http://%20www.economist.com/node/21548963/">For the first time ever,the number of poor people is declining everywhere</a>.
That&#39;s a pretty amazing statistic if it&#39;s true, so I couldn&#39;t help but check
it out.</p>

<p>The article starts out by telling us:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>The best estimates for global poverty come from the World Bank’s Development
Research Group, which has just updated from 2005 its figures for those
living in absolute poverty (not be confused with the relative measure
commonly used in rich countries). The new estimates show that in 2008, the
first year of the finance-and-food crisis, both the number and share of the
population living on less than $1.25 a day (at 2005 prices, the most
commonly accepted poverty line) was falling in every part of the world. This
was the first instance of declines across the board since the bank started
collecting the figures in 1981 (see chart).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Right off the bat I&#39;m a little skeptical that <strong>the best</strong> estimates for
global poverty from anywhere in the world come from...a bank -- much less the
almighty World Bank.  But that&#39;s just me, let&#39;s dig into the actual numbers.</p>

<p>The research from the World Bank defines a person in poverty as one who lives on
less than $1.25 a day, and these dollars are fixed at 2005 dollar values.  So
their data tells us that, when adjusted for inflation, there are a smaller
percentage of people today living on less than $1.25 a day, than there have
been since 1981.</p>

<p>I couldn&#39;t help but wonder what the dollar has done since 1981. I found this
interesting chart from the Federal Reserve:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/dolllarindex.png" title="&#34;US Dollar Index&#34;" alt="&#34;US Dollar Index&#34;"></p>

<p>Isn&#39;t it rather interesting that the dollar index is virtually at the lowest
point it has been at since records began (even before 1981)?</p>

<p>I&#39;m a big believer that hard assets have more stable value over time than
fiat, government-printed paper, which means they are a better measure of
value over time -- a better yardstick, so to speak -- so I also looked up a chart from
<a href="http://pricedingold.com">princedingold</a> comparing US dollars with the price
of gold since the late 18th century (the relatively straight lines in the
beginning are due to the fact that the dollar was linked to gold up until 1971):</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/USD-1787-log.png" title="&#34;US Dollar Vs. Gold&#34;" alt="&#34;US Dollar Vs. Gold&#34;"></p>

<p>Again, we see that the US Dollar vs Gold is at an all time low.  What this
tells us is that, nominally, the value of the US dollar is the lowest it has
been ever.  This means that someone living off of $1.25 in 1981 was doing
much better off than someone living off of $1.25 today.  Based off the first
chart above, let&#39;s say the dollar index was around 100 in 1981, and that it
stands right around 70 today.  That means that today, you would have to live
on $1.79 just to have the same standard of living you had in 1981 with $1.25.
If you use the gold values from the second chart it&#39;s even worse.  Based on that
measurement you&#39;d have to live on closer to $3 a day today to have the same
standard of living you had in 1981 -- nearly 300% more!</p>

<p>These examples are all nominal, of course, and the World Bank tells us that they
are adjusting everything to 2005 dollars (what they did before 2005 I have no
idea).  I don&#39;t know exactly how they are doing this adjustment, but I would
guess they are using something like the <a href="http://www.bls.gov/cpi/">CPI</a>.</p>

<p>Now, the CPI doesn&#39;t make for that good of a yardstick either.  It has been
changed many times over the years, and during the recent housing boom,
the CPI didn&#39;t even include house prices!  Right now the CPI doesn&#39;t include
food or gas prices, the two things whose price is increasing the most!  So how
accurate can the CPI really be, and how accurate can adjustments made off of it
(or any similar measure) really be compared to real value.  For those
interested, <a href="http://advisorperspectives.com/dshort/">Doug Short</a> has some great
alternative inflation measurements and
<a href="http://advisorperspectives.com/dshort/updates/Inflation-Since-1872.php">writeups</a>
that are worth a look.</p>

<p>My point here isn&#39;t really to prove their numbers wrong, but just to point out
a few of the many problems with data such as this.  Measuring poverty by those
living on X oz. of gold would have it&#39;s problems as well, so there is no perfect
solution.  But if we did use the gold measurement, and adjust based on that,
I&#39;d bet that the conclusion is probably <em>very</em> different.</p>

<p>Look, we all want poverty to go down, but the World Bank in particular has
an interest in making sure countries the world over want to take more of
their strings-attached loans to &#39;better their countries&#39;.  We&#39;ve seen how the
banks act in the United States, does anyone think they act in the interest of
the poor?</p>

<p>My personal opinion is that global poverty is likely on the decline, especially
over the long run.  I believe there are many today worse off than they were
last year, the year before, or even in 1981, but in aggregate, I think it&#39;s
likely that the global standard of living is increasing.  We are a resilient,
resourceful, and creative species, and we continue to progress and better our
standard of living.</p>

<p>The sensational title from the Economist states &quot;For the first time ever...&quot;
Really?  Since the dawn of the first humans on this earth, this is the first
time global poverty has ever declined?  I think someone was fishing for readers,
and hey, they got this reader to bite.  But let&#39;s take their data with a huge
grain of salt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Startups, Day Jobs, and Impact]]></title>
    <link href="/2012/03/19/on-startups-day-jobs-and-impact.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-19T04:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2012/03/19/on-startups-day-jobs-and-impact</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#39;s been about 5 months since I quit my day job and decided to plunge
head-first into the world of <a href="https://www.crowdtilt.com">startups</a>.
It&#39;s been an amazing ride so far, and I know I&#39;ve only begun to scratch
the surface of what&#39;s to come.</p>

<p>Don&#39;t get me wrong, I&#39;ve been incredibly fortunate to have some
<a href="https://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/webmailus_acquired_by_rackspace.php">great</a>
<a href="http://www.siteworx.com">jobs</a> with some incredibly
intelligent and talented people.  I&#39;ve learned
a lot along the way, and the experiences have been great.  The breakneck
pace of the past 5 months at <a href="https://www.crowdtilt.com">crowdtilt</a>, however,
is something I hadn&#39;t experienced before.  It&#39;s amazing how fast
perspectives can change.</p>

<p>With a small team (we&#39;ve currently got 2 developers) everyone has lots
of autonomy, responsibility, and most importantly (for me, at least)
each person has the ability to have a <strong>huge</strong> impact on the business (and
on people&#39;s lives).  Every person on the team is empowered to make decisions,
move as quickly as possible, and really own the things they do.  This is often
lost at larger corporations, where there&#39;s more beauracracy and processes to
get in the way of what us developers really want to be doing (coding and
getting things done &trade;).  In this environment abstract teams own things,
while people and individuality are lost.  Thus far I&#39;ve been really happy with
our focus, our pace, and our ability to keep tedious processes and long
decision-chains to a bare minimum.</p>

<p>Ownership and impact are two things that I think are really big in a startup
environment -- in fact, they&#39;re huge.  To really own the tasks at hand while 
taking on the responsibility of getting them done and making the hundreds of
small decisions that inevitably come with any project is really rewarding
and also satisfying.  When you are given the power to make these decisions
it helps the company move faster, which is very exciting, but it also adds
creativity and brainpower to the companies growth engine -- after all,
startups don&#39;t just want instruction-followers, they want creators and doers.</p>

<p>As we look to grow our team, we&#39;re going to put a lot of focus on keeping these
things in tact.  We want to make sure everyone is empowered, self-motivated and
has access to all the tools they need to do great work.  We want to find
people who have a passion for creating great things, thrive with autonomy, and
want the opportunity to have a very large impact every single day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git Processes, Scripts and Ideas]]></title>
    <link href="/2012/03/16/git-processes-scripts-and-ideas.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-16T02:56:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2012/03/16/git-processes-scripts-and-ideas</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately I&#39;ve been refining some of my git processes (as well as learning
a lot about git along the way).  I thought I&#39;d write up a post to share
some of the ways i&#39;ve been using git.</p>

<h2>Workflow</h2>

<p>Our typical workflow at <a href="https://www.crowdtilt.com">crowdtilt</a> is pretty
standard.  We have a <code>dev</code> branch, a <code>master</code> branch, and various feature/topic
branches.  We also make heavy use of github for pull requests/code reviews.</p>

<p>When I go to develop a new feature/bugfix, I start by creating a new branch
off of the latest <code>dev</code>, and start coding.  I often make many small commits
along the way because I&#39;m a strong believer in commit early, commit often.  I
also push my branch to github pretty frequently just to be on the safe side.</p>

<p>Once my feature branch has been tested, and is ready to be merged into <code>dev</code>,
I rebase all of my small commits into 1.  We try to keep all of our PR&#39;s to 1
commit just to keep our git history clean, useful, and readable as a history
of concise and (hopefully) small changes.  To do this, I have been simply
using:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">$ git rebase -i dev
</code></pre></div>
<p>This will drop me into vim with a lits of all the commits between <code>dev</code>&#39;s
<code>HEAD</code> and my current branch&#39;s <code>HEAD</code>.  It will look something like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">pick 1dea3ff Commit #1
pick 57a5a28 Commit #2
pick 3f21ade Commit #3
</code></pre></div>
<p>I simply squash all the commits into one by replacing <code>pick</code> with <code>s</code> on
all but the first line.  This gives me something like this:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">pick 1dea3ff Commit #1
s 57a5a28 Commit #2
s 3f21ade Commit #3
</code></pre></div>
<p>This tells git that I want to squash all of these commits into one.  Once
I quit and save it&#39;ll then let me give a new commit message for my new
mega-commit.</p>

<p>Here I try to follow convention with a short summary on the first line,
and then a lengthier description describing my feature/bugfix/whatever in
a paragraph below that.</p>

<p>Once I have my branch neatly tidied up with one descriptive commit, it&#39;s time
to pull request.</p>

<h2>Pull Requests and hub</h2>

<p>I love the github web interface for reviewing code and checking out diffs, but
it is very tedious to go to the website, find your branch, and make the pull
request through the web interface.  Enter
<a href="https://github.com/defunkt/hub">hub</a> -- a wonderful command-line tool that
lets you create pull requests (amongst lots of other cool things) right
from the command line.</p>

<p>To do a pull request right from my coding directory, I can simply run:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">$ hub pull-request &quot;Pull Request Title&quot;
</code></pre></div>
<p>The caveat here is that hub (and github, too) default all pull requests
to merge into the <code>master</code> branch.  We always merge into <code>dev</code>, and then
merge <code>dev</code> into <code>master</code> when we are ready to deploy changes to production
(I&#39;ll talk more about our deploy processes in another article). So to get
it to merge into <code>dev</code>, we must run the following:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">$ hub pull-request &quot;Pull Request Title&quot; -b dev
</code></pre></div>
<p>This is closer to what we need, but by default what this will do is setup
a pull request on github from <code>throughnothing:feature-branch</code> to
<code>crowdtilt:dev</code>.  It does this because it assumes that I want to do a pull
request from my users fork to the original users repository.  We don&#39;t really
have each developer fork our repos, we just all work on the same repo in our
own branches, so we really want it to do a pull-request from
<code>crowdtilt:feature-branch</code> to <code>crowdtilt:dev</code>.  This means we need:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">$ hub pull-request &quot;Pull Request Title&quot; -b dev -h crowdtilt:feature-branch
</code></pre></div>
<p>It seemed really simple at first, but now it&#39;s a lot to type.  Time for some
<code>~/.bashrc</code> magic.  To make things as simple as possible for our development
process, I&#39;ve written this little bash function to put in our <code>~/.bashrc</code> files
to smooth things out:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">pullreq() {
    [ -z $BRANCH ] &amp;&amp; BRANCH=&quot;dev&quot;
    HEAD=$(git symbolic-ref HEAD 2&gt; /dev/null)
    [ -z $HEAD ] &amp;&amp; return # Return if no head
    REMOTE=`cat .git/config | grep &quot;remote \&quot;origin\&quot;&quot; -A 2 | tail -n1 | sed 's/.*:\([^\/]*\).*/\1/'`

    hub pull-request -b $BRANCH -h $REMOTE:${HEAD#refs/heads/} $1
}
</code></pre></div>
<p>This accepts a <code>BRANCH</code> environment variable that can be set, but will default
to <code>dev</code> (which is pretty much 90+% of our use cases).  It also parses the
github user that the origin of the repository</p>

<p>Not only has <code>hub</code> greatly streamlined our pull request process, but when
combined with the bash function, it eliminates errors of pull requesting
feature branches to be merged into <code>master</code> (and even having them
<em>accidentally</em> merged into master directly -- that never happens, right?)
instead of <code>dev</code>.</p>

<p>Using this script, when we&#39;re ready to do a deploy and merge <code>dev</code> into <code>master</code>
we simply can run (from the <code>dev</code> branch):</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">$ BRANCH=master pullreq
</code></pre></div>
<p>And the pull request will be created to merge dev into master so we can review
it on github.</p>

<h2>Managing Branch Chaos</h2>

<p>I said earlier that I was a believer in commit early, commit often.  Well, I&#39;m
also a believer in small branches.  We pretty much make branches for everything.
Even if it&#39;s just a simple css change, or a one-line bug-fix, I like to
quarantine changesets into a branch of their own.  So many times i&#39;ll be
caught in the middle of a simple change and have to go tend to something else.
Having branches lets me quickly commit &quot;saving my place&quot;, or &quot;WIP&quot;
in my branch, and get to work looking at something in another branch.
My feature branch will be there waiting for me when I&#39;m ready to go back to it.</p>

<p>Additionally, smaller branches make for smaller merges, which are easier to
review, and less prone to introducing glaring errors that could have been
caught.</p>

<p>A side-effect of all this branching and pushing and merging is that you can
quickly get confused about which branches have been merged and which haven&#39;t.
The list of branches shown on github and on the command line grows to make it
harder for you to find the branches you still care about.  So of course,
we can delete the branches as we go, but this is very tedious to do so
frequently as you have to delete the branch locally, and on github:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">$ pullreq
# Review code on github
$ git checkout dev &amp;&amp; git merge feature-branch &amp;&amp; git push origin dev
$ gut branch -D feature-branch  # delete feature-branch locally
$ git push origin :feature-branch # delete feature-branch on github
</code></pre></div>
<p>Enter more <code>~/.bashrc</code> goodness.  I wanted a way to streamline
this process as well because i was typing the above waaay too frequently, so
I came up with two handy bash functions:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">git_purge_local_branches() {
  [ -z $1 ] &amp;&amp; return
  BRANCHES=`git branch --merged $1 | grep -v '^*' | grep -v 'master' | grep -v 'dev' | tr -d '\n'`
  echo &quot;Running: git branch -d $BRANCHES&quot;
  git branch -d $BRANCHES
}

git_purge_remote_branches() {
  [ -z $1 ] &amp;&amp; return
  git remote prune origin

  BRANCHES=`git branch -r --merged $1 | grep 'origin' | grep -v '/master$' | grep -v '/dev$' | sed 's/origin\//:/g' | tr -d '\n'`
  echo &quot;Running: git push origin $BRANCHES&quot;
  git push origin $BRANCHES
}
</code></pre></div>
<p><code>git_purge_local_branches()</code> will -- as the name implies -- purge local
branches that have been merged into the branch you give it.  And
<code>git_purge_remote_branches()</code> will do the same but it will remove the branches
from the <code>origin</code> remote.  So every now and then, when we get a lot of branches
hanging around getting in our way, we can clean them up with:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">$ git_purge_local_branches dev
$ git_purge_remote_branches dev
</code></pre></div>
<p>And of course, because running 2 commands just became too much, I created
<code>git_purge</code>...one purge to rule them all:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-text" data-lang="text">git_purge() {
  branch=$1
  [ -z $branch ] &amp;&amp; branch=&quot;dev&quot;
  git_purge_local_branches $branch
  git_purge_remote_branches $branch
}
</code></pre></div>
<p>So now its super easy to manage our branch chaos.  When I start to see too
many branches building up, I can simply <code>git_purge</code> and it&#39;ll wipe out
any branches locally and on the origin that have already been merged
into dev.  Then we&#39;re back to a blissful state of branch zen.</p>

<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>That pretty much sums up my current git processes.  I really enjoy how
streamlined things have become, how well our processes work, and how easy it is
to keep our branches clean and clutter-free while at the same time encouraging
us to branch, branch, branch!</p>

<p>How are you using git?  Tell me how I can make my workflow even better and more
kick-ass :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="/2012/03/15/hello-world.html"/>
    <updated>2012-03-15T22:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2012/03/15/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello.  This is a test.  This is only a test.</p>

<p><code>perl Perl
say &quot;Hello, World&quot;;
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A New Continent For Us: Asia]]></title>
    <link href="/2011/07/16/new-continent-for-us-asia.html"/>
    <updated>2011-07-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2011/07/16/new-continent-for-us-asia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just dropped Angelle off at the airport for her 5 week jaunt in India.  She&#39;s
fortunate to be going for work, so mostly all of her expenses are paid for, and
it is a wonderful opportunity for her to go.  I&#39;ll be meeting up with her in a
few weeks for the last leg of the trip as well, and I can&#39;t wait.</p>

<p>Neither of us have been to Asia before, so we are both very excited to see a new
continent.  New cultures, places, and experiences are always exciting, and I&#39;m
thrilled to see what India has to offer us.</p>

<p>I&#39;m going to be going for just over 2 weeks, and I&#39;m planning to pack as light
as I can, though my laptop (for work) and DSLR will take up the most space.
I&#39;ll put together a post with my packing list once I&#39;ve got everything nailed
down, but for now I&#39;ve got a few weeks by myself here in DC for some running,
bike riding, and quiet reflection before I head off to a new continent.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[City Life - DC]]></title>
    <link href="/2011/07/15/city-life.html"/>
    <updated>2011-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2011/07/15/city-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We’ve moved.  For the first time in my life I now live in a big city.  It’s only
been a week, but so far I’m loving it.  We moved into the Dupont area of DC last
Saturday, and have been getting settled in all week.  I most enjoy taking Belle
(our white Maltise) on multiple walks during the day throughout the city.
Night-time cruises on my bike have also been great as the weather has been
perfect all week.</p>

<p>Our living space is a little bit smaller than before, but I consider that a
bonus.  It forces us to re-evaluate our possessions, and find what is necessary.
We got rid of a bed, a dresser, and downsized our wardrobes and kitchen things.
It actually feels like we have more space, and getting rid of old junk is very
freeing.</p>

<p>As for the city life, there are so many people out and about all the time , and
so much going on, it can sometimes seem like overload.  Lucky for us, Rock Creek
Park provides a quiet getaway from the hustle and bustle of the city when
needed.  We have been enjoying night time strolls along the Dupont area, and
just wandering aimlessly to get to know the area.  I’m excited for what the
future holds here.</p>

<p>It took Zeus and Belle a few days to get adjusted to the new place, but I think
they are both getting pretty situated now.  Zeus no longer hides in the kitchen
cabinets all day, and Belle already knows how to find her way back home after a
good walk.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Now]]></title>
    <link href="/2011/06/26/now.html"/>
    <updated>2011-06-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2011/06/26/now</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>All we have is now.  I try to remind myself of this when I get caught up in
reminiscing about the past, or worrying about the future.  The past no longer
is, and the future never will be.  All we have is the present moment; now and
always.</p>

<p>If we aren&#39;t happy in this present moment, can we ever be happy?  Being here,
now, is one of the things I&#39;m continually working on.  I&#39;m far from perfect, and
probably drift away from the present moment thousands of times a day.  The trick
is catching yourself when this happens, and being mindful of it.  Keep
persistently catching yourself, and reminding yourself that right now is all
you&#39;ve got.  Breathe.  The more we can catch ourselves slipping out of the
present, the more aware we can become of ourselves, our surroundings, and the
lives we actually lead.  Now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Single Speed]]></title>
    <link href="/2011/04/08/single-speed.html"/>
    <updated>2011-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2011/04/08/single-speed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like Biking.  I&#39;m drawn to the simplicity and elegance of the bicycle.  I&#39;ve
been biking to work pretty regularly (read: whenever its above 35 degrees), for
a while now, and I love it.</p>

<p>One way to make biking even simpler is to get rid of the gears.  I&#39;ve been
looking for a decent bike to turn into a single speed for a while, and finally a
deal came up on craigslist that I couldn&#39;t pass up...and it was already a single
speed.</p>

<p>I rode it to work and back twice this week (12 miles each way), and I&#39;m loving
it.  It is definitely a little more strenuous at times, but its so simple, and
you never have to think about changing gears.  When you&#39;re on a single speed,
the only thing you can do is pedal, and maybe that&#39;s the way it should be.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Christmas Gift You Can Give]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/12/08/the-best-christmas-gift-you-can-give.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-08T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/12/08/the-best-christmas-gift-you-can-give</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Remember, if Christmas isn't found in your heart, you won't find it under a tree.</p><footer><strong>Charlotte Carpenter</strong></footer></blockquote>

<p><strong>The best Christmas gift you can give is your time.</strong> Your friends and family more than likely have everything they really need, but what they often may not get enough of is your time. Spend time with them. Quality time. Listen to them. Laugh with them. Let them know you are there for them.</p>

<h2>Gifts are just more stuff</h2>

<p>Stuff that most of us don&#39;t need. If you have money you&#39;d like to get rid of during the Christmas season, give it to a charity, or someone genuinely in need. Explain to others what you are doing, and even link back to this post if you think it will help them see why quality time and good company are better than any gift.</p>

<h2>Time is the most valuable commodity in the world</h2>

<p>Sharing some of yours with others means more than that iPad, golf club, or purse you could buy them (and its better for the planet as well). Stop reading blogs and go share your time with someone special. You won&#39;t regret it. Go. Now.</p>

<h2>Other Great Christmas Posts</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://zenhabits.net/bah/">The Case Against Buying Christmas Presents</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.becomingminimalist.com/2010/11/26/35-gifts-your-children-will-never-forget/">35 Gifts Your Children Will Never Forget</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.farbeyondthestars.com/1-simple-strategy-to-save-2000-this-holiday-and-make-everyone-love-you-forever/">1 Simple Strategy To Save $2000 this Holiday and Make Everyone Love You Forever</a></li>
<li><a href="http://guynameddave.com/2010/12/christmas-and-kids-no-guilty-gifts/">Christmas And Kids - No Guilty Gifts</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Barefoot]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/12/06/running-barefoot.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/12/06/running-barefoot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Running should be free, man.</p><footer><strong>Christopher McDougall</strong></footer></blockquote>

<p>Barefoot running (and running with minimalist footwear) is a rapidly growing trend today.  Encouraged by Christopher Mcdougall&#39;s Born to Run, and activists such as Barefoot Ken Bob and Barefoot Ted, the movement really seems to be taking off. When I first heard about barefoot running earlier this year, I was very skeptical. People don&#39;t REALLY run barefoot, do they?!</p>

<p>Yes, they do, and I now count myself amongst their growing ranks. I can tell you from personal experience that running barefoot has changed my life. I truly believe that it can change yours too.</p>

<p>You see, before March of this year I was not a runner. I couldn&#39;t tell you the last time I had run (for fun anyway), and I certainly didn&#39;t enjoy running. If you had told me then that I would be in love with running in just a few short months, I certainly would have laughed.</p>

<h2>How Fast Things Change</h2>

<p>As I write this today, not only am I in love with running, but in October I finished my first marathon (which I will write more about shortly) -- and I’m looking forward to running more!</p>

<p>How did I go from docile couch potato to a running addict? The real secret for me was barefoot running.</p>

<h2>Why Barefoot Running?</h2>

<p>Simply put, barefoot running is wonderful. It releases your inner child and makes you feel like a kid again. Barefoot running allows your body to teach you how to run the way you are designed to.</p>

<p>I&#39;m convinced that the main thing preventing most people from running is that they don&#39;t enjoy it. This was certainly true for me. I had tried running in the past but just never found it fun. Barefoot running changed this for me completely.</p>

<h2>Steps to Running Barefoot</h2>

<p>If you&#39;re interested in barefoot running, you&#39;ve already got everything you need to get started (great news for all you minimalists!). I will just provide some simple steps that I&#39;ve learned from my own experiences running barefoot.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Start Slowly. Very slowly. Seriously, you can&#39;t go too slowly. Your feet have likely been in shoe-casts for many many years, and your muscles and bones have probably atrophied to an extent. It will take some time to get them strengthened to where they need to be before you begin putting a lot of raw mileage on your feet. Too much too soon and you pulling muscles, tearing up your soles, and even stress fractures in your feet. I can&#39;t stress this point enough.</p></li>
<li><p>Love it. This should come pretty easily, but if it doesn&#39;t, stop and figure out why. If you aren&#39;t enjoying it, really don&#39;t continue until you find the joy in it. You don&#39;t want to run miserably anyway, right?</p></li>
<li><p>Don&#39;t Push Yourself. When you or your feet feel tired, stop. You don&#39;t want to overwork your feet, and once you start pushing yourself, you may lose the enjoyment. If you resolve to call it a day once your body tells you to, you&#39;ll be able to continue to get in good runs day after day and enjoy every minute of them.</p></li>
<li><p>Don&#39;t measure your progress. Counterintuitive, I know, but people often get too obsessed with their mileage and their times. Just focus on your body and learn to understand what it is telling you. This will improve your form and help increase your distance naturally over time at a pace that your body can handle. Measuring how far you run may cause you to become frustrated, or to try to push yourself to do too much too soon. Avoid this by not using a gps, stopwatch, or other measuring device. This will also help keep your mind clear and enable you to achieve flow in your running.</p></li>
<li><p>The rest will come naturally. If you follow the 4 steps above, the rest will fall into place. Your mileage will increase, your form will improve, and you will be loving it.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>Hopefully this short introduction to barefoot running will motivate you to get out there and start enjoying running. Remember to take it slow and make sure you are having fun.</p>

<h2>Links</h2>

<p>Here are some additional links about barefoot running that you may find useful:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.barefootted.com/">Barefoot Ted</a> - One of the leaders of the barefoot movement thanks to &quot;Born To Run&quot; and Christopher McDougal. He is starting his own running sandal company (Luna Sandals), and has a very useful discussion group on his site.</li>
<li><a href="http://therunningbarefoot.com/">Running Barefoot</a> - Barefoot Ken Bob&#39;s (the original barefoot runner) site is a wealth of information on barefoot running!</li>
<li><a href="http://birthdayshoes.com/">Birthday Shoes</a> - The unofficial fan site of vibram five fingers and other minimalist shoes. Full of great reviews, tips, and user stories.</li>
<li><a href="http://chrismcdougall.com/blog/">Chris McDougall</a> - Author of the great book, &quot;Born to Run.&quot; He found barefoot running by accident (just like many of us, I believe) and tells the thrilling story of his experiences in Mexico with the Tarahumara Indians.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 Ways to Enjoy Your Commute]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/12/04/5-ways-to-enjoy-your-commute.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/12/04/5-ways-to-enjoy-your-commute</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Patience is something you admire in the driver behind you and scorn in the<br/>one ahead.</p><footer><strong>Mac McCleary</strong></footer></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, it seems as if many of us dread our morning commute. We don&#39;t
even like to think about it -- all the traffic, the stopping, the starting,
the rushing, the worrying. But it doesn&#39;t have to be this way.</p>

<p>You can enjoy your commute. It will take some lifestyle adjustments, some
time, and a re-thinking of your routine, but you can do it. Below are five
steps that you can use to start improving and enjoying your commute today.</p>

<h2>1. Wake Up Earlier</h2>

<p>By far the number one thing you can do to make your commute more enjoyable
is to wake up earlier. They say that time is money, but time is also
happiness. How often do you have time to simply sit, and enjoy the morning?
Waking up earlier gives you the time to clear your head, relax, and get
ready at your own pace. Instead of getting dressed while guzzling down your
morning coffee, sit down and just sip. Maybe you can even observe a
beautiful sunrise without worrying about being late.</p>

<p>Of course, you don&#39;t want to wake up earlier at the expense of losing even
more sleep (I&#39;m assuming that you aren&#39;t getting enough already), so you
will need to find ways to go to bed earlier. Cutting out some TV or internet
browsing at night is well worth the extra sleep you&#39;ll get, and certainly
worth the calm, relaxed morning you&#39;ll have the next day.</p>

<h2>2. Bike (or Run/Walk) to Work</h2>

<p>I started biking to work about a year ago, and my only regret is not doing
it sooner. For some of you this may not be an option if you live too far
from work, but if you&#39;re close enough, give this a shot! You&#39;ll love it.
Biking to work is exhilarating, like being a child again. It&#39;s great for the
environment, your body, and your wallet.</p>

<p>It may take you longer to get to work this way (you&#39;re getting up earlier
now, right?), but you&#39;ll be having fun, enjoying the outdoors, and avoiding
the stresses of your old commute.</p>

<p>Get out of your metal box, and experience the world on your next commute!</p>

<h2>3. Eliminate Advertisements and Background Noise</h2>

<p>If you&#39;re one of the lucky ones who can do number two above, then you&#39;ll
already have this one covered (don&#39;t wear headphones while biking/running!).
For the rest of you, try to limit -- or eliminate completely -- your
exposure to advertising during your commute. I think many of us keep the
radio on for background noise -- to keep our mind numb during the drive.
Stop doing this. It can be a distraction from your driving, and it doesn&#39;t
help clear your mind, or reduce your stress. If your mind needs something to
chew on, roll down a window and listen to the sounds of the world around
you, it&#39;s really much better than whatever your favorite radio host is
rambling on about, and you may be surprised by how much you enjoy this.</p>

<p>You don&#39;t need to be bombarded by advertisements and talk show hosts pushing
their interests on you. Without these distractions, you&#39;ll give your mind a
rest, and you&#39;ll likely be more focused on your driving.</p>

<p>If you really can&#39;t stand having the radio off completely, try to stick with
some CDs or music from an mp3 player. That way, you can choose music that
you know you like, and avoid the commercials and radio static.</p>

<h2>4. Go Slowly</h2>

<p>Since you&#39;ve woken up earlier, you now have enough time to get to work, so
go slowly. Take your time. Enjoy the trees changing colors, the squirrels
playing, the colors of the early morning sun. You may even notice beautiful
things in your own neighborhood that you hadn&#39;t seen before (I know I did).
Don&#39;t get angry when someone cuts you off, just let it happen, knowing that
you&#39;ve got plenty of time to get where you&#39;re going.</p>

<h2>5. Be Present. Breathe.</h2>

<p>Going slowly will help you to be present. Try to be completely present and
aware of each moment as it slips by. Be aware of your surroundings. A great
way to focus right now is to simply breathe. Breathe in and out. Pay
attention to each breath and the movement of the breath throughout your
body. At first it may be difficult to stay focused, but over time it will
become more natural, and you&#39;ll look forward to your commute as a calm,
mind-clearing start to your work day.</p>

<p>If you practice these steps regularly, you&#39;ll begin to look forward to your
commute. Your commute will become a form of mental preparation for the day
ahead, free of the stress, worrying, and rushing.</p>

<p>How are you working to improve your morning routine and commute?</p>

<blockquote><p>Leave sooner, drive slower, live longer.</p><footer><strong>Unknown</strong></footer></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Successful People Read Books]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/12/03/successful-people-read-books.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/12/03/successful-people-read-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>I find television to be very educating. Every time somebody turns on the set, I go in the other room and read a book.</p><footer><strong>Groucho Marx</strong></footer></blockquote>

<p>I was re-reading an old
<a href="http://www.ridiculouslyextraordinary.com/101-life-lessons/">blog post</a> by
<a href="http://www.ridiculouslyextraordinary.com/">Karol Gadja</a> over at Ridiculously Extraordinary about life lessons, when one item on his list suddenly stood out and got my mind working.</p>

<h2>Successful People Read Books</h2>

<p>Its true. In fact, after reading it, it seems so obvious, but its something I hadn&#39;t thought of in this way before. I follow a lot of bloggers who (I think) write very well and are successful, and almost all of them seem to devour books pretty regularly.</p>

<p>Of course, this all makes perfect sense. Reading expands our knowledge base, and introduces us to new, creative ideas. Reading also helps expose us to different writing styles and different cultures -- both of which can improve our own writing.</p>

<p>Those who read regularly are keeping their minds active and constantly bombarded with new experiences, thoughts, questions, provocations, and images. Under these circumstances it would be hard for the mind to not pop out a unique idea of its own.</p>

<p>If you want to be a well-rounded, successful, thought-filled individual, turn off the TV and pick up a book. What are you reading today?</p>

<blockquote><p>The man who does not read good books has no advantage over the man who can't read them.</p><footer><strong>Mark Twain</strong></footer></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Art]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/12/02/art.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/12/02/art</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>art is simple<br>
art is complex<br>
art is colorful<br>
art is blind<br>
art is funny<br>
art is serious<br>
art is frustrating<br>
art is liberating<br>
art is concrete<br>
art is abstract<br>
art is flagrant<br>
art is humble<br>
art is<br>
we are<br>
art  </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Steppin' Out for Diabetes Run]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/10/23/steppin-out-ford-diabetes.html"/>
    <updated>2010-10-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/10/23/steppin-out-ford-diabetes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="jekyll-mapping"
                        data-latitude=""
                        data-longitude=""
                        data-layers="http://api.flickr.com/services/feeds/photoset.gne?set=72157625227380948&nsid=45105880@N00&lang=en-us&georss=1 https://raw.github.com/throughnothing/gpx/master/2010/20101023.gpx"
                        data-locations=""
                        data-title="Steppin' Out for Diabetes Run"
                        style="height:320px;width:730px;"></div>
<p>Today my company, <a href="http://www.siteworx.com">Siteworx</a>, was one of the sponsors of the <a href="http://main.diabetes.org/site/TR/StepOut/DistrictofColumbiaMetroArea?pg=entry&amp;fr_id=7239">Steppin&#8217; Out for Diabetes</a> walk/run in Washington D.C.  The course starts and ends by the Nationals stadium in southern D.C.</p>
<p>We got there pretty early, before many other people were there.  At least parking was easy!  Plus we had to support our Siteworx crew that was out there even earlier than us setting up the nice booth :)</p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1437/5109403986_ccf2f3f523_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1437/5109403986_ccf2f3f523_z.jpg" title="Pre-walk/run setup" alt="Pre-walk/run setup" /></a></p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1316/5108806297_cf1c743837_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1316/5108806297_cf1c743837_z.jpg" title="Siteworx Booth" alt="Siteworx Booth" /></a></p>
<p>It was a pretty chilly morning, we all wore vibrams to the event to keep our feet warm, but Andy and I were planning on shedding the vibrams for the run.</p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1235/5109403350_4cb9be14a1_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1235/5109403350_4cb9be14a1_z.jpg" title="Before the run,<br />
by the Siteworx booth" alt="Before the run,<br />
by the Siteworx booth" /></a></p>
<p>After walking around for a bit and checking out all that there was to see (not much, except for a pretty good dance group doing some cool stuff), it was time to shed the shoes!</p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1356/5109405878_db6da2cc4d_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1356/5109405878_db6da2cc4d_z.jpg" title="Shedding the<br />
Vibrams and Injinjis" alt="Shedding the<br />
Vibrams and Injinjis" /></a></p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1423/5109406534_878910336f_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1423/5109406534_878910336f_z.jpg" title="Pre-race Feet" alt="Pre-race Feet" /></a><br />
After some waiting around, the &#8220;race&#8221; was off to a&#8230;.slow start.  We initially had to weave through the hundreds of walkers until we got out of the stadium and into the streets where there was more room to get out in front of all the walkers.  Once we got to that point it was smooth sailing&#8230;.almost.</p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1329/5109108626_8221b2055c_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1329/5109108626_8221b2055c_z.jpg" title="Andy and Kevin Running on the DC Streets" alt="Andy and Kevin Running on the DC Streets" /></a></p>
<p>The main complaint I have is that the course was very poorly marked in many locations, and it seemed other runners and walkers were having difficulty following and seeing the signs as well.  I&#8217;m still not sure if we did the entire course correctly (we definitely made a few wrong turns and had to loop back), but according to my iPhone we only ended up running 4 miles, not the complete 5. But at least we made it to the finish, and we were feeling great.</p>
<p><a href="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4127/5109407228_323c49ac43_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4127/5109407228_323c49ac43_z.jpg" title="Me, Andy, and Kevin at the finish line" alt="Me, Andy, and Kevin at the finish line" /></a></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimal Text Editors]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/10/22/minimal-text-editors.html"/>
    <updated>2010-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/10/22/minimal-text-editors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately I&#8217;ve been wanting to do more writing.  I want to jot down my thoughts more often, and hopefully get better at both writing them down, and using writing as a way to organize and record my thoughts.  I&#8217;ve almost always used vim as my text editor, development platform, and just about everything else you can imagine, but lately i&#8217;ve been looking for something that might help me avoid the distractions of being in a terminal, and having multiple windows visible behind what i&#8217;m working on (usually browsers) etc.</p>
<p>So in looking for some good minimal text editors, I came across two that I am going to be trying out.  The first, and probably more minimal of the two is <a href="http://pyroom.org">PyRoom</a>.  PyRoom is written in python and basically takes up your entire screen, with the middle section (height/width is adjustable) used for simple, plain text.  It doesn&#8217;t have the power of vim in terms of keyboard shortcuts, but it does basic editing, and allows multiple buffers.  It does have a few keyboard shortcuts for closing buffers, switching buffers, etc., which is nice, but I want my insert/normal modes!  As I said, PyRoom is very minimal, with no menus or anything except for one preferences dialog that you can get to with Ctrl+p.  The colors are customizable, as well as the height/width as I said before, but other than that there isn&#8217;t much to customize.</p>
<p>The other editor I will be trying out is <a href="http://gottcode.org/focuswriter/">FocusWriter</a>.  FocusWriter is actually cross-platform, so I can use it on my Mac at work if I so desire.  It has a lot more features, and is a lot less minimal than PyRoom &#8212; it does rich text editing, has menus, and even a hidden menu bar that can be pulled up.  When FocusWriter is run, the interface seems about the same as PyRoom, but by moving the mouse to the top, or bottom of the screen, you can show the menus, tab-bars, and toolbars that normally stay hidden from view.</p>
<p>One nice feature about FocusWriter that I like is that you can set a daily goal for writing, such as 30 minutes, or 1,000 words, etc.  This may be nice as I try to get myself to do more writing, so that I could set goals and try to force myself to actually just write every day, no matter how terrible it may be :P</p>
<p>So I&#8217;m going to try these two editors out for a while and see how it goes.  So far I&#8217;ve typed this whole post in PyRoom and like it.  It keeps the distractions at bay and lets me focus on my writing.  I feel like I may end up falling back to vim eventualy just because I love the power of vim for editing text, but it seems that these editors may provide a better level of focus that may be worth it.  We shall see.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Workplace Velociraptor Incidents]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/10/21/velociraptor-attacks.html"/>
    <updated>2010-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/10/21/velociraptor-attacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Fortunately, it has now been 18 days since the last Velociraptor Incident in our Siteworx Reston Headquarters.  Let&#8217;s hope the trend continues.</p>
<p><a href="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1239/5102658706_26bbbfccde_z.jpg"><img src="http://farm2.static.flickr.com/1239/5102658706_26bbbfccde_z.jpg" title="Velociraptor Incidents" alt="Velociraptor Incidents" /></a></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creative Commons' Branding Confusion]]></title>
    <link href="/2010/10/20/creative-commons--branding-confusion.html"/>
    <updated>2010-10-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/2010/10/20/creative-commons--branding-confusion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Nina Paley recently <a href="http://questioncopyright.org/CC-branding-confusion">wrote about</a> some of the issues she has had releasing some of her work under a Creative Commons-Share Alike license, as well some of the confusion brought about by the various creative commons licenses.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>About a year and a half ago I released my film Sita Sings the Blues under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike license. That license allows truly free distribution, including commercial use, as long as the free license remains in place. But my experience is that most people see the words &#8220;Creative Commons&#8221; and simply assume the license is Non-Commercial &#8212; because the majority of Creative Commons licenses they&#8217;ve seen elsewhere have been Non-Commercial.</p>
<p>This is a real problem. Some artists have re-released Sita remixes under Creative Commons Non-Commercial licenses. Many bloggers and journalists assume the non-commercial restrictions, even when the license is correctly named:</p>
<p>The film was made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike License, allowing third parties to share the creative content for non-commercial purposes freely as long as the author of the content is attributed as the creator of the work. &#8212;Frontline, India&#8217;s National Magazine</p>
<p>Initially I tried to explain what &#8220;ShareAlike&#8221; means, and asked &#8220;Sita&#8221; remixers to please switch to ShareAlike, per the terms of the ShareAlike license under which I released it. I felt like an ass; I don&#8217;t want to be a licensing cop. After a while, mis-identifications of the project&#8217;s license became so widespread I gave up trying to correct them. &#8220;Creative Commons&#8221; means &#8220;Non-Commercial&#8221; to most people. Fighting it is a sisyphean task.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>There seems to be a lot of confusion around Creative Commons with many people assuming that it is <em>always</em> non-commercial, and others not understanding creative commons licenses at all.  The real tragedy is that Nina is trying to essentially have her work be open and available to anyone for any purpose, and people are still not understanding that.  Nina concludes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I need a license that people understand. I&#8217;m tempted by the <span class="caps">WTFPL</span> but I would have to fork it to add a copyleft provision. The Do Whatever You Want And Don&#8217;t Restrict Others From Doing Whatever They Want Public License? <span class="caps">WTFDROPL</span>?</p>
<p>Are there any other useable Copyleft licenses out there that aren&#8217;t associated with non-commercial restrictions? I&#8217;m open to suggestions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is an interesting question.  Being one who is very interested in the topic, I am very aware of the differences between the various Creative Commons Licenses, and never really thought there would be such confusion, but obviously that was a wrong assumption.</p>
<p>In some searching for other <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copyleft">copyleft</a> licenses, I came across the <a href="http://artlibre.org/licence/lal/en">Free Art License</a>, which may be of some use to Nina.</p>
<p>This brings up another interesting thought, however, and that is with regards to copyleft licenses versus public domain, or &#8220;uncopyright.&#8221;  You may have noticed that all the material on my site(s) is &#8220;uncopyrighted&#8221; and that I release all of the content into the public domain.  Reading this article did make me think again about copyleft vs. public domain, as copyleft has the restriction that anyone creating derivative works from the original work, is forced to release their derivative works under the same license without restrictions.  This seems like it may have the benefit that society as a whole is guaranteed to have access to share, use, and benefit from any derivative works in exactly the same way that it could from the original.  It does, however, impose the creator&#8217;s will onto others, and I still find this unnatural.  Copyleft essentially makes use of copyright to achieve its ends, but I&#8217;m still not sold that copyright is the way to go.  I will continue to release my content into the public domain, and use that as my &#8220;license&#8221; of choice wherever possible.</p>
<p>As another side note, when is <a href="http://www.flickr.com">flickr</a> going to add a &#8220;public domain&#8221; option to their licensing options?  For now I am forced to chose Creative Commons-Share Alike, as that is the most liberal license (and a copyleft license), but I would prefer to be able to chose &#8220;public domain&#8221;.  Come on flickr, can&#8217;t we get that?!</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>

